<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Golang on raph haXx </title>
      <generator uri="https://hugo.spf13.com">Hugo</generator>
    <link>http://raph.es/tags/golang/index.xml/</link>
    
    
    <copyright>Raphael Estrada 2011-2014</copyright>
    <updated>Sun, 16 Sep 2012 19:43:00 &#43;0100</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving the Comfort Zone</title>
      <link>http://raph.es/blog/2012/09/Leaving-the-Comfort-Zone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2012 19:43:00 &#43;0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://raph.es/blog/2012/09/Leaving-the-Comfort-Zone/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, what a &amp;ldquo;blah&amp;rdquo; title. But I&amp;rsquo;m in a hurry now. As all the internets have undoubtedly noticed, I haven&amp;rsquo;t blogged in a while. I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy with shit, and to break out of it I&amp;rsquo;m dumping out a quick post. In fact, future posts will probably be a bit shorter, just to get anything out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_0&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s been happening&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my more recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.galaktor.net/2012/02/yet-another-attempt-at-levelling-up-my.html&#34;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; (read: months old) mentioned that I was once again attempting to move my computing life into Linux. Well, the good news is, I succeeded. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent about 98% (pretty random gut-feeling number) of my time on Crunchbang in the past months, and there&amp;rsquo;s no looking back so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could blame my laziness with regards to blogging on a missing driver for The Internet or something. But really I&amp;rsquo;ve seen only a minor driver issue with my built-in webcam&amp;rsquo;s mic, which I have also resolved - so Linux has been working great on my laptop. Yet I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a Windows guy, and switching to Linux had one big challenge in particular: coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to make pretty serious changes to my usual workflow to get coding on Linux. I wanted to leave the MS world I am used to behind and go as native as possible, Which was pretty much the definition of what all those &amp;ldquo;leave your comfort zone&amp;rdquo; mantras are about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_1&#34;&gt;Going hardcore&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Determined to embrace the command-line world which is Linux, I decided to go the whole length and use Emacs as my (sort of) IDE. And the learning curve was a lot easier than I expected - you hear a lot of bullshit about how hard it is and whatever. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t. Yes, you need to learn some shortcuts, big deal. It&amp;rsquo;s just a powerful text editor with a bunch of plugins. From day one I&amp;rsquo;ve been running it in console mode (-nw), and it not only looks like straight out of a cliche hacker movie, it&amp;rsquo;s also really lightweight and fast. Loving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Language was trickier - I&amp;rsquo;m mainly a .NET guy, and I have played with Mono before, but I again wanted to go as &amp;ldquo;non-Windows&amp;rdquo; as possible. And I wanted to use the opportunity to learn new languages. So I played around with clojure for a while - and I might write a bit on it separately, but long story short: I&amp;rsquo;m not impressed. It&amp;rsquo;s essentially yet another abstraction above of where I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last years (C#, which is Java-ish). But contrary to common opinion, I don&amp;rsquo;t think imperative programming is necessarily evil, and I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself leaning toward the more low-level side of things again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;toc_2&#34;&gt;Coding in Go&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cut to the chase, I discovered Go, which is like C on steroids, and it immediately felt like what I need. I&amp;rsquo;ve gone from zero to productive in a few days, and I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy so far. Again, I&amp;rsquo;ll be posting on this later. I have a little side-project going which I will write about on this here blog soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize: I barely use Windows at all, just for the occasional game, so very rarely .I feel at home on Linux now, and I&amp;rsquo;m coding happily in Go on Emacs with some help of Go&amp;rsquo;s great command line tools. I&amp;rsquo;d say this attempt at moving to Linux was finally a success, and I&amp;rsquo;ve not only left my comfort zone, I pretty much inverted it - and it&amp;rsquo;s been a great ride so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;hugs and kisses xoxox
lol&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>